<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--BeerTools Pro 1.5.24--><RECIPES><RECIPE><NAME>Brown-Eyed Girl 4</NAME><VERSION>1</VERSION><TYPE>All Grain</TYPE><STYLE><VERSION>1</VERSION><STYLE_GUIDE>BJCP</STYLE_GUIDE><TYPE>Ale</TYPE><CATEGORY>Porter</CATEGORY><NAME>Robust Porter</NAME><CATEGORY_NUMBER>12</CATEGORY_NUMBER><STYLE_LETTER>B</STYLE_LETTER><PROFILE>Moderately strong malt flavor usually features a lightly burnt, black malt character (and sometimes chocolate and/or coffee flavors) with a bit of roasty dryness in the finish.  Overall flavor may finish from dry to medium-sweet, depending on grist composition, hop bittering level, and attenuation. May have a sharp character from dark roasted grains, although should not be overly acrid, burnt or harsh.  Medium to high bitterness, which can be accentuated by the roasted malt.  Hop flavor can vary from low to moderately high (US or UK varieties, typically), and balances the roasted malt flavors.  Diacetyl low to none.  Fruity esters moderate to none.</PROFILE><INGREDIENTS>May contain several malts, prominently dark roasted malts and grains, which often include black patent malt (chocolate malt and/or roasted barley may also be used in some versions).  Hops are used for bittering, flavor and/or aroma, and are frequently UK or US varieties.  Water with moderate to high carbonate hardness is typical.  Ale yeast can either be clean US versions or characterful English varieties.</INGREDIENTS><NOTES>Although a rather broad style open to brewer interpretation, it may be distinguished from Stout as lacking a strong roasted barley character.  It differs from a brown porter in that a black patent or roasted grain character is usually present, and it can be stronger in alcohol.  Roast intensity and malt flavors can also vary significantly.  May or may not have a strong hop character, and may or may not have significant fermentation by-products; thus may seem to have an "American" or "English" character.</NOTES><EXAMPLES>Great Lakes Edmund Fitzgerald Porter, Meantime London Porter, Anchor Porter, Smuttynose Robust Porter, Sierra Nevada Porter, Deschutes Black Butte Porter,  Boulevard Bully! Porter, Rogue Mocha Porter, Avery New World Porter, Bell's Porter, Great Divide Saint Bridget's Porter</EXAMPLES><OG_MIN>1.048</OG_MIN><OG_MAX>1.065</OG_MAX><FG_MIN>1.012</FG_MIN><FG_MAX>1.016</FG_MAX><COLOR_MIN>22</COLOR_MIN><COLOR_MAX>35</COLOR_MAX><ABV_MIN>4.8</ABV_MIN><ABV_MAX>6.5</ABV_MAX><IBU_MIN>25</IBU_MIN><IBU_MAX>50</IBU_MAX></STYLE><BREWER>Damon Gunther</BREWER><BATCH_SIZE>18.92706</BATCH_SIZE><BOIL_SIZE>22.56139</BOIL_SIZE><BOIL_TIME>60</BOIL_TIME><EFFICIENCY>83.05999</EFFICIENCY><HOPS><HOP><VERSION>1</VERSION><NAME>Challenger</NAME><ORIGIN>UK</ORIGIN><NOTES>Popular bittering hop used primarily in British ales and lagers. Mild to moderate aroma, but quite spicy.</NOTES><AMOUNT>0.0283495</AMOUNT><TIME>60</TIME><SUBSTITUTES>Northern Brewer</SUBSTITUTES><TYPE>Both</TYPE><FORM>Pellet</FORM><USE>Boil</USE><ALPHA>6.9</ALPHA><BETA>4.25</BETA><COHUMULONE>22.5</COHUMULONE><MYRCENE>36</MYRCENE><HUMULENE>29</HUMULENE><CARYOPHYLLENE>9</CARYOPHYLLENE><FARNESENE>0</FARNESENE><HSI>0.4</HSI></HOP><HOP><VERSION>1</VERSION><NAME>Willamette</NAME><ORIGIN>USA</ORIGIN><NOTES>This hop is used for finishing and dry hopping American and British style ales. Aroma is mild and pleasant ans slightly spicy</NOTES><AMOUNT>0.0283495</AMOUNT><TIME>5</TIME><SUBSTITUTES>Fuggles, Styrian Goldings, E.K. Goldings.</SUBSTITUTES><TYPE>Bittering</TYPE><FORM>Pellet</FORM><USE>Boil</USE><ALPHA>4.7</ALPHA><BETA>3.5</BETA><COHUMULONE>32.5</COHUMULONE><MYRCENE>50</MYRCENE><HUMULENE>25</HUMULENE><CARYOPHYLLENE>0</CARYOPHYLLENE><FARNESENE>0</FARNESENE><HSI>0.37</HSI></HOP></HOPS><FERMENTABLES><FERMENTABLE><VERSION>1</VERSION><NAME>Maris Otter Pale Ale Malt</NAME><ORIGIN>UK</ORIGIN><NOTES>A principal ingredient of cask ales using heritage barleys.</NOTES><AMOUNT>3.175147</AMOUNT><TIME>0</TIME><TYPE>Grain</TYPE><SUPPLIER>Thomas Fawcett</SUPPLIER><RECOMMEND_MASH>TRUE</RECOMMEND_MASH><COLOR>2.5</COLOR><MAX_IN_BATCH>0</MAX_IN_BATCH><YIELD>80.5</YIELD><COARSE_FINE_DIFF>1.25</COARSE_FINE_DIFF><MOISTURE>3</MOISTURE><PROTEIN>9.5</PROTEIN><DIASTATIC_POWER>45</DIASTATIC_POWER></FERMENTABLE><FERMENTABLE><VERSION>1</VERSION><NAME>Aromatic Malt</NAME><ORIGIN>North America</ORIGIN><NOTES>Golden rich color and a smooth malty flavor. Characteristics &amp; Applications: • Munich-style malt that will contribute an intensely malty flavor and aroma. • Use in any beer style for additional maltiness. • Produced from AMBA/BMBRI recommended 2-Row Malting Barley varieties.</NOTES><AMOUNT>0.4535924</AMOUNT><TIME>0</TIME><TYPE>Grain</TYPE><SUPPLIER>Briess</SUPPLIER><RECOMMEND_MASH>TRUE</RECOMMEND_MASH><COLOR>20</COLOR><MAX_IN_BATCH>0</MAX_IN_BATCH><YIELD>77</YIELD><COARSE_FINE_DIFF>1.28</COARSE_FINE_DIFF><MOISTURE>2.5</MOISTURE><PROTEIN>11.7</PROTEIN><DIASTATIC_POWER>15</DIASTATIC_POWER></FERMENTABLE><FERMENTABLE><VERSION>1</VERSION><NAME>Biscuit Malt</NAME><ORIGIN>Belgium</ORIGIN><NOTES>Features: Unique and very special Belgian malt. Lightly kilned, then lightly torrefied up to 160°C. Usage: All special beers and as well for English ales, brown ales and porters. Recommended proportion: up to 15% of the grist. Characteristics: Biscuit malt produces a very pronounced "toasty" finish in the beer. Imparts a warm bread and biscuit like aroma and flavour. Biscuit Malt promotes a light to medium warm brown colour to the mash. This malt is used to improve the roasted flavour and aroma that characterize ales and lagers lending the subtle properties of black and chocolate malts. No enzymes. Must be mashed with malts having a surplus of diastatic power.</NOTES><AMOUNT>0.2267962</AMOUNT><TIME>0</TIME><TYPE>Grain</TYPE><SUPPLIER>Castle Malting</SUPPLIER><RECOMMEND_MASH>TRUE</RECOMMEND_MASH><COLOR>23.05</COLOR><MAX_IN_BATCH>0</MAX_IN_BATCH><YIELD>76.99168</YIELD><COARSE_FINE_DIFF>1.5</COARSE_FINE_DIFF><MOISTURE>4.7</MOISTURE><PROTEIN>0</PROTEIN><DIASTATIC_POWER>0</DIASTATIC_POWER></FERMENTABLE><FERMENTABLE><VERSION>1</VERSION><NAME>Special B Malt</NAME><ORIGIN>Belgium</ORIGIN><NOTES>Features: Very special Belgian dark malt, obtained through specific double drying process. Usage: Abbey ales, Trappist ales, dubbels, porters, brown ales, doppelbocks. Recommended proportion: 10%. Characteristics: Is used to produce a deep red to dark brown-black colour and fuller body. Unique flavour and aroma. Gives much colour and raisin-like flavour. Imparts a rich malty taste and a hint of nut and plum flavour. May substitute Chocolate and Black malt if bitterness is not desired.</NOTES><AMOUNT>0.2267962</AMOUNT><TIME>0</TIME><TYPE>Grain</TYPE><SUPPLIER>Castle Malting</SUPPLIER><RECOMMEND_MASH>FALSE</RECOMMEND_MASH><COLOR>113.65</COLOR><MAX_IN_BATCH>0</MAX_IN_BATCH><YIELD>76</YIELD><COARSE_FINE_DIFF>1.5</COARSE_FINE_DIFF><MOISTURE>4</MOISTURE><PROTEIN>0</PROTEIN><DIASTATIC_POWER>0</DIASTATIC_POWER></FERMENTABLE><FERMENTABLE><VERSION>1</VERSION><NAME>Crystal Malt 60°L</NAME><ORIGIN>American</ORIGIN><NOTES>Sweet caramel flavor, deep golden to red color. For dark amber and brown ales.</NOTES><AMOUNT>0.2267962</AMOUNT><TIME>0</TIME><TYPE>Grain</TYPE><SUPPLIER></SUPPLIER><RECOMMEND_MASH>FALSE</RECOMMEND_MASH><COLOR>60</COLOR><MAX_IN_BATCH>20</MAX_IN_BATCH><YIELD>73.58</YIELD><COARSE_FINE_DIFF>2.04</COARSE_FINE_DIFF><MOISTURE>4</MOISTURE><PROTEIN>0</PROTEIN><DIASTATIC_POWER>0</DIASTATIC_POWER></FERMENTABLE><FERMENTABLE><VERSION>1</VERSION><NAME>Crystal Malt 80°L</NAME><ORIGIN>American</ORIGIN><NOTES>Body and Richness. Distictive Nutty flavor and or sweet, smooth caramel flavor and a red to deep red color. For porters, old ales.</NOTES><AMOUNT>0.2267962</AMOUNT><TIME>0</TIME><TYPE>Grain</TYPE><SUPPLIER></SUPPLIER><RECOMMEND_MASH>FALSE</RECOMMEND_MASH><COLOR>80</COLOR><MAX_IN_BATCH>20</MAX_IN_BATCH><YIELD>71.41</YIELD><COARSE_FINE_DIFF>2.1</COARSE_FINE_DIFF><MOISTURE>4</MOISTURE><PROTEIN>0</PROTEIN><DIASTATIC_POWER>0</DIASTATIC_POWER></FERMENTABLE><FERMENTABLE><VERSION>1</VERSION><NAME>Chocolate Malt</NAME><ORIGIN>North America</ORIGIN><NOTES>Rich roasted coffee flavor. Characteristics &amp; Applications: • Chocolate Malt is used in all beer styles for color adjustment with minor or no flavor contribution. • Use 1-10% for desired color in Porter and Stout Beer. • The chocolate flavor is very complementary when used in higher percentages in Brown Ales, Porters, Stouts and other Dark Beers. • Produced from AMBA/BMBRI recommended 6-Row Malting Barley varieties.</NOTES><AMOUNT>0.1133981</AMOUNT><TIME>0</TIME><TYPE>Grain</TYPE><SUPPLIER>Breiss</SUPPLIER><RECOMMEND_MASH>FALSE</RECOMMEND_MASH><COLOR>350</COLOR><MAX_IN_BATCH>0</MAX_IN_BATCH><YIELD>73</YIELD><COARSE_FINE_DIFF>2</COARSE_FINE_DIFF><MOISTURE>6</MOISTURE><PROTEIN>0</PROTEIN><DIASTATIC_POWER>0</DIASTATIC_POWER></FERMENTABLE></FERMENTABLES><MISCS><MISC><VERSION>1</VERSION><NAME>Irish Moss</NAME><ORIGIN>Common</ORIGIN><NOTES>A dried red-brown marine algae. Fining agent to remove large proteins. Negatively charged polymer attracts positively charged protein-tannin complexes (extracted from grain husks and hops) during the boil. This action is aided by the clumping of proteins in the boiling process. Irish moss settles to the bottom of the brew kettle with spent hops and hot break material at the end of the boil.</NOTES><AMOUNT>0.0049289</AMOUNT><TIME>15</TIME><TYPE>Other</TYPE><USE>Boil</USE></MISC></MISCS><YEASTS><YEAST><VERSION>1</VERSION><NAME>California Ale</NAME><ORIGIN></ORIGIN><NOTES>This yeast is famous for its clean flavors, balance and ability to be used in almost any style ale. It accentuates the hop flavors and is extremely versatile.</NOTES><AMOUNT>1</AMOUNT><LABORATORY>White Labs</LABORATORY><PRODUCT_ID>WLP001</PRODUCT_ID><FORM>Liquid</FORM><TYPE>Ale</TYPE><FLOCCULATION>Low</FLOCCULATION><ATTENUATION>76.5</ATTENUATION><MIN_TEMPERATURE>20</MIN_TEMPERATURE><MAX_TEMPERATURE>22.77778</MAX_TEMPERATURE></YEAST></YEASTS><WATERS/><MASH/><NOTES>v4:9/29/2018 8:30am5.25 gal in HLT, drained to 2 gal, 152 mash.v2:Calculated OG: 1.053  (75% efficiency)Calculated FG:  1.0134/7/2013 8:45am4.75 gal in HLT to heat up in parts, sparge water later.  52 to 168 in ~35 minMash tun temp good, but after grains added, ~149.  Heated more water to 168 to increase up to 150 after 15 minutesHeated 6.25 gal of sparge water to 182Mash tun lost 1 degree in 1 hour (approx)Stopped sparge water at just under 2 gal to go, collected 6.25 gal when mash tun wet dry, last runnings reading was 1.012Full boil after 3 hours 30 minutesPropane running low, may have frozen up, boil was soft, so extended 10 minutes after tank changeChilling required stirring at the end, but tap cold enough without ice.  Let run while draining (splashing) to fermenter.  10 min aeration  Pitched at 65, fermention in basementOG: 1.059   (83% efficiency)4/12/2013 7:00pmRack to secondary.  Keeping in pantry at 70.SG: 1.0204/22/2013 7:30pmBottlingFG: 1.017 (close to 1.016)</NOTES><OG>1.059183</OG><FG>1.017053</FG><DATE>Sep 29, 2018</DATE><CARBONATION>2.5</CARBONATION><PRIMING_SUGAR_NAME/><CARBONATION_TEMP>20</CARBONATION_TEMP><PRIMING_SUGAR_EQUIV>1</PRIMING_SUGAR_EQUIV></RECIPE></RECIPES>